David Lamar McDonald Papers
David L. McDonald Papers
1930-1967
McDonald, David L. (David Lamar), 1906-1997.
2 linear ft.
Audiotapes, correspondence, printed material, other items from the American admiral.
2709837
Biographical History
David L. McDonald (1906-1997) was a United States Navy officer for more than forty years. He attended the U.S. Naval Academy (class of 1928) and later studied at the National War College (1950-1951). Commissioned as an ensign in 1928, he was designated a naval aviator in 1931 and eventually rose to the rank of admiral in 1963. He served aboard several navy ships early in his career and commanded three others, including the U.S.S. Coral Sea; other postings included instructor at the Pensacola Naval Air Station, commander of the Sixth Fleet, chief of Naval Operations, and commander of U.S. Naval forces in Europe. He saw active duty during World War II and Vietnam, and receivedthe Navy Distinguished Service Medal (twice), the Legion of Merit, and a Bronze Star. He retired with the rank of Admiral.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The David L. McDonald Papers consists of audiorecordings, subject files, and writings.
Audiorecordings include conferences, interviews, and news briefings.
Subject files contains official Navy biographical material and a few clippings about McDonald.
Writings contains addresses and remarks delivered on various occasions, articles by McDonald, and statements before various Congressional committees.
Arrangement of the Collection
Arranged by type and within that by title or subject, with the exception of the audiotapes, which are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
has numerous collections relating to military history; please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; McDonald, David L. (David Lamar), 1906-1997.; United States. Navy -- Officers.; Audiotapes.; Correspondence.; Speeches (documents); Admirals.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of H. E. Hetu, 1965.
Inventory
- Audiorecordings
  - Chief of Naval Operations Press Conference, Naval War College, 01/16/1964; mcdonald_dl_001; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Admiral McDonald Press Conference, AHO Building, United States Naval Air Station, Atlanta, 02/22/64; mcdonald_dl_002; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - Georgia’s Admiral, 02/22/1964; mcdonald_dl_003; Audio portion of video-tape program recorded interview of Chief of Naval Operations Admiral David L. McDonald at WSB-TV Atlanta, Georgia conducted by Ray Moore, News Director.; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - Admiral McDonald Press Conference at US Naval Postgraduate School, Monterey, California, 03/13/1964; mcdonald_dl_004; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - Chief of Naval Operations New Briefing, Ft. Leavenworth, Kansas, 03/19/1964; mcdonald_dl_005; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Press Conference, Norfolk, Virginia, 04/18/1964; mcdonald_dl_006; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Conference at Armed Forces Staff College, Norfolk, Virginia, 04/22/1964; mcdonald_dl_007; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Conference, Tulsa, Oklahoma, 05/14/1965; mcdonald_dl_008; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - Press Conference of Admiral David L. McDonald, Chief of Naval Operations. Buenos Aires, Argentina, 06/02/1965; mcdonald_dl_009; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Press Conference in Rio De Janeiro, Brazil, 06/03/1965; mcdonald_dl_010; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Press Conference at Naval Air Stations in Alameda and Lemoore, California, 08/02/1965; mcdonald_dl_011; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Press Conference in Seattle, Washington, 08/27/1965; mcdonald_dl_012; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - David Lamar McDonald Press Conference at New Orleans, Louisiana, 11/25/1965; mcdonald_dl_013; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Press Conference at the Conrad Hilton Hotel, Chicago, Illinois before the Armed Forces Benefit Football Game, 09/02/1966; mcdonald_dl_014; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Press Conference at Fort Garry Hotel, prior to Chief of Naval Operations speech to the Annual Convention of the Canadian Navy League, Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada, 09/29/1966; mcdonald_dl_015; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 3)
  - Remarks by Admiral David L. McDonald, United States Navy, Chief of Naval Operations at the Public Affairs Workshop, Pentagon, Washington, DC, 10/18/1966; mcdonald_dl_016; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 3)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Interview by Joe Campbell of the Mutual Broadcasting System in Admiral’s office, 11/22/1966; mcdonald_dl_018; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 3)
  - Chief of Naval Operations on NBC, Washington, DC (Today Show), 11/29/1966; mcdonald_dl_019; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 3)
  - Chief of Naval Operations appearance on WGTV - “Men and Ideas”, 01/24/1967; mcdonald_dl_020; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 3)
  - Arrival/Press Conference. Sydney, Australia. Chief of Naval Operations - Coral Sea Celebration, 04/30/1967; mcdonald_dl_021; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 3)
  - Arrival/Press Conference. Canberra, Australia. Chief of Naval Operations - Coral Sea Celebration, 05/01/1967; mcdonald_dl_022; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 3)
  - Arrival/Press Conference. Brisbane, Australia. Chief of Naval Operations - Coral Sea Celebration, 05/03/1967; mcdonald_dl_023; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 3)
  - Arrival/Press Conference. Adelaide, Australia. Chief of Naval Operations - Coral Sea Celebration, 05/10/1967; mcdonald_dl_024; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 3)
  - Arrival/Press Conference. Melbourne, Australia. Chief of Naval Operations - Coral Sea Celebration, 05/11/1967; mcdonald_dl_025; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 3)
  - Television Interview Chief of Naval Operations; Coral Sea Visit, Melbourne, Australia, 05/12/1967; mcdonald_dl_026; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 3)
  - Press Conference. Hobart, Australia. Chief of Naval Operations, Coral Sea Celebration, 05/13/1967; mcdonald_dl_027; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 3)
  - Press Conference, Christ Church, New Zealand, Chief of Naval Operations - Coral Sea Celebration, 05/15/1967; mcdonald_dl_030; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 4)
  - Arrival/Press Conference. Perth, [Australia]. Chief of Naval Operations, Coral Sea Celebration, 05/17/1967; mcdonald_dl_028; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 4)
  - News Conference, Wellington, New Zealand, Chief of Naval Operations - Coral Sea Celebration, 05/17/1967; mcdonald_dl_029; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 4)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Press Conference, Christ Church, New Zealand, Chief of Naval Operations - Coral Sea Celebration, 05/18/1967; mcdonald_dl_031; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 4)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Farewell Luncheon at Sheraton Park (part 1), 07/31/1967; mcdonald_dl_032; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 4)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Farewell Luncheon at Sheraton Park (part 2), 07/31/1967; mcdonald_dl_033; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Farewell Luncheon at Sheraton Park (part 3), 07/31/1967; mcdonald_dl_034; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Farewell Luncheon at Sheraton Park (part 4), 07/31/1967; mcdonald_dl_035; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Chief of Naval Operations - Change of Command at Naval Academy (part 1, copy), 08/01/1967; mcdonald_dl_036; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Chief of Naval Operations - Change of Command at Naval Academy (part 2, copy), 08/01/1967; mcdonald_dl_037; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Department of Defense Press Conference, Pentagon, Washington, DC, 11/16/1996; mcdonald_dl_017; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 3)
  - Interview of Admiral McDonald by Mr. Watson (part 1), undated; mcdonald_dl_038; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Interview of Admiral McDonald by Mr. Watson (part 2), undated; mcdonald_dl_039; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Address. Australia Version, undated; mcdonald_dl_040; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Chief of Naval Operations Address. New Zealand Version, undated; mcdonald_dl_041; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
  - Department of Defense Public Affairs Audio -Visual Division audio tape recording of Admiral McDonald, Chief of Naval Operation, Guest of Honor, undated; mcdonald_dl_042; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 5)
- Subject files
  - Biographical material, photographs, summary of naval service, official Navy biography (Box 1)
  - Clippings about, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Addresses and remarks, 1963-1965; change of command ceremonies, ship launches, U.S. Navy and Naval Academy events, various organizations' conferences and meetings (including officers' wives), senior Swedish military officers, etc.; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Articles by, 1964; Seabees, future of the Navy, etc. (Box 1)
  - Interviews, 1964-1965; Today show, U.S. News and World Report (Box 1)
  - Statements to Congressional committees, 1963-1965; Joint Committee on Atomic Energy, Senate Armed Services committee, Appropriations Committee, others; topics include military posture, military appropriations, and nuclear propulsion (Box 1)